hi I'm coach bre andur this video is
going to discuss the bent over row now
there are a number of ways to do a good
bent over row um here I have the barbell
on the floor here's my favorite way to
do the barbell but I actually like the
hex bar Ben overo the most which is
right here which I will go over in a
second but I'm going to go over three
ways to do it with a
barbell first I am going to get around a
shoulder shoulder width position I'm not
going to like if my deadlift position
was right here see how the bar is close
to my shins I'm not going to get that
close with the bend over up I'm actually
going to back up a little bit so the bar
is over my toes all right I will bend
over and I'm going to keep High hips
kind of like where I would be in a
straight leg
deadlift and I could take a narrow grip
or a wide grip I like going a just
slightly wider than you would like with
a deadlift grip double over hands
because this is a great grip exercise if
you do it right so I like double over
hands and I don't like to rest the bar
on the ground in between reps but I like
to come down all the way notice my torso
Position will not change much I am not
flexing extending the hips my torso
stays in constant position so come down
like
this chest up
chin tucked or a neutral so I'm looking
down so my spine is straight I'm not
hyperextended I not Flex my hips are
high I'm using my glutes and my
hamstrings to keep me in place I hold on
to the bar from here I like doing a
double overhand grip slightly wider than
shoulder width from here I just raise
the bar off the ground about an inch
right here now I'm going to road to my
chest just like
this okay notice the things I did not
heave I came all the way up to my chest
I'm not coming to my belly or up to my
you know Upp or just I come right to
around
here and my trunk was very horizontal is
it's harder you can't use as much weight
this way and notice that did not come to
the ground on each rep and
reset now that's my favorite way to do
the B over
row but
uh another way to do them is called the
penl row This was um popularized by
Glenn penl a popular Olympic
weightlifting coach and it's similar to
what I just did with a a couple of minor
differences you will notice that uh with
the penl row it is similar you cannot
use as much weight as you can with a
more upright row that I'll show you next
but nevertheless this is a very good Ben
over Ro variation but it is pretty it's
pretty Advanced you know Advanced
lifters can do this but beginners they
can't do this properly it's too
complicated for them with the penl row
you are going to get into position you
restart each rep from the ground and you
actually actually are going to round the
upper back slightly and as you row
upwards you are going
to extend the thoracic spine while
rowing and then you come down and reset
what's nice about this is that because
you touch the ground each time you do
start in a low position you don't it um
protects you from skimping on your range
of motion so the penley r looks like
this I'm rounded I'm going to extend my
spine like this while
rowing up so it looks like
this so that's a pen
lro I like my rowing variation a little
bit more because you don't reset the r
reps um you work the grip
better however his variation is awesome
and it's really good for advanced
lifters Glenn spec speculates that when
you do some arching of the back some
thoracic extension at the same time he
thinks that that gets you more lat EMG
activity I think he might be right but
uh anyway that's a pretty Advanced
variation that
beginners aren't really good at but
Advanced lifs can do and now a final
variation with the regular barbell is
the the Yates row and this was named
after Dorian Yates and he liked to use
it as kind of a bicep and a lower lat
exercise he went heavier with the weight
and you're going to have a much more
upright trunk
position um again you're going to use
heavier weight and you're going to pick
the bar
up in a underhand grip position like
this start from the top come down to
about knee level you can use heavier
weights and then you row to your lower
belly like
this so that's another variation you can
go heavier on that
one so now I've shown you three
different Ben overow
variations um I'm going to show you some
common
mistakes most beginners you'll watch
them and they'll be rounded over like
this you'll see them like
this you don't want this rounded spun
you want to be like this in good
position okay you want to be nice and
arched some people um I just showed you
that the Yates row you can be more
upright that's fine if
you are an advanced lifter who knows how
to control his muscles but if you're a
beginner loading on a lot of plates and
you look like this you're just kind of
like this going
and you're heaving and using momentum
and jarring you know your joints that's
not good you're just stroking your ego
you're not building
muscle so one final variation that I
want to show you this is my favorite is
the hexar B
overow this takes some practice in
getting used
to but
uh as you can see here I'm standing in
the middle of a hex bar okay as I I'm
going to get into position and I
actually have to row backwards a little
bit what I like about this barbell so
when or using the hex bar when you use a
traditional barbell you can only come up
to here but when you have a hex bar you
can get that last little squeeze come up
higher through scapular
retraction so I'm going to get into
position good posture good head and neck
position I lift the bar slightly off the
ground and
then just like that some people if you
rast straight up the the back of the bar
will hit your butt that's why you have
to Glide rearward a little
bit okay I just showed you four
different B over row variations all four
are excellent there are different ways
to do a a good bed overow you just have
to know which is best for you
all right thanks for watching